Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ב Mem Bais
42. We pick up four lines, five lines from the bottom on
מ"א עמוד ב', Mem Aleph Amud Bais, שאלו את בן זומא. Sha'alu
es Ben Zoma. So just to review what we said yesterday because
we have some very key הלכות halachos here about ברכות. brachos. We
said first of all that a ברכה bracha on wine exempts שאר
מיני משקים, she'ar minei mashkim, other liquids. Important הלכה halacha that a
lot of people are not aware of. I checked, I double-checked yesterday
in the משנה ברורה, Mishna Berurah, he brings down a range of
opinions from those that say it's only when you drink a lot
of wine and that you're really sort of almost קובע סעודה koveia
seudah on wine and you're drinking an enormous amount of wine, there
are those that say even the tiniest amount. He sort of comes
up with, decides, the more of a middle position that if you
drink a like a מלא לוגמיו mlo lugmav of like, you know,
most of your cheek, like a majority of the רביעית, revi'is, this
idea that בורא פרי הגפן borei peri hagafen exempts other משקים. mashkim.
But people are not aware about this, particularly when they go to
a קידוש kiddush or whatever, they start drinking before they've made המוציא.
Hamotzi.
He rejects the opinion that says that just hearing and being יוצא
yotzei the ברכה bracha without drinking should exempt you. He says you
don't have to worry about that position, but there are those that
say that. So just if you answer אמן amen to a קידוש
kiddush that you might be exempt. But that's, you know, basically he
totally rejects that, the משנה ברורה. Mishna Berurah. And that's you say
to drink a מלא לוגמיו? mlo lugmav? Yeah, the position he seems
to be there. Right, that's משנה ברורה. Mishna Berurah. And that's wine
exempting. Then we get to the much bigger question which is what
ברכה bracha when we make המוציא Hamotzi in a meal, what's covered?
So רש"י Rashi says at the ברכה ראשונה, bracha rishona, רש"י Rashi
says basically things that are there fundamentally to serve ללפת את הפת,
lefapes es hapas, to serve as some type of an accompaniment to
the bread. And רש"י Rashi says if you have something that's really
a staple of the meal but not meant to accompany bread, like
oatmeal or something like that, רש"י Rashi says you would have a
separate ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. רש"י Rashi conceptually thinks it's about the
bread. תוספות Tosafos and the way we פוסקן pasken is that it's
about the idea of meal, but things that are not seen as
מחמת הסעודה machmas haseudah require special ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona.
What does it mean מחמת הסעודה? machmas haseudah? So the general explanation
is that things that are there primarily for taste and not for
being for filling.
So although there are some that say that nowadays that everybody has
let's say a dessert, that's considered מחמת הסעודה. machmas haseudah. But the
general consensus is is that if it's not there to fill, if
it's there primarily just for the taste, then it's not מחמת הסעודה,
machmas haseudah, leads to a lot of questions about certain appetizers, certain
desserts. So let's say a dessert is a מזונות, mezonos, let's say
it's an appetizer but it's a standard type of an appetizer, lot
of questions about that. The last category is things that are after
the meal, and there not only does it require ברכה ראשונה bracha
rishona but even a ברכה אחרונה, bracha achrona, even if you haven't
said ברכת המזון Birchas Hamazon yet. תוספות Tosafos says that we don't
really have that phenomena nowadays. Yes, we have dessert nowadays, but the
idea that it's completely detached from the meal, you just haven't said
a ברכת המזון, Birchas Hamazon, that we don't have. It's always considered
to be connected to the meal, so you will never have a
case of eating something during the meal that you make a ברכה
אחרונה bracha achrona for, but you might have a ברכה ראשונה bracha
rishona when it's not considered directly connected to the meal. That's the
question. Just conceptually? So okay, very quickly. Yeah, because when you say
we have all these מחלוקות machlokos in them and this opinion and
that opinion, wouldn't you think you say ספק ברכות להקל? safek brachos
l'hakeil? So yeah, that tends to be the general position, but you
know, you have to first decide what do you consider מספק. misafek.
Right, exactly. And you first פוסקן pasken and then what you feel
you can't פוסקן pasken then you apply those principles to it. The
other problem Michael raises and I'll just say one word about this
is, you know, okay, when there's a question how to פוסקן pasken
and you really don't know, say ספק ברכות להקל safek brachos l'hakeil
be done with it. And you could have said that. But as
I've been mentioning, there's one line in the גמרא Gemara but a
consistent theme in תוספות Tosafos has been based on the מהר"ם מרוטנבורג,
Maharim MiRothenburg, oh, just have it during, after you said המוציא, Hamotzi,
so to cover yourself because the flip side in ברכות brachos of
נהנין hanehenin of ספק ברכות להקל safek brachos l'hakeil is אסור ליהנות
מן העולם הזה בלא ברכה. assur l'hanos min ha'olam hazeh belo bracha.
So it's not just a question of do I have a מצוה
mitzvah of a ברכה, bracha, but the question is okay, but do
I want to be deriving benefit, הנאה, hanao, which I'm not entitled
to? So that's why although you're right, in principle ספק ברכות להקל
safek brachos l'hakeil and that is the general approach of פוסקים, poskim,
but there's also this other strand of let's just try to find
a way to play it safe because you don't want to get
הנאה hanao without a ברכה. bracha. Okay, so now let's pick up
five lines from the bottom of מ"א עמוד ב', Mem Aleph Amud
Bais, שאלו את בן זומא. Sha'alu es Ben Zoma. They asked בן
זומא Ben Zoma מפני מה אמרו דברים הבאים מחמת הסעודה בתוך הסעודה
אינם טעונים ברכה לא לפניהם ולא אחריהם? mipnei mah amru devarim habaim
machmas haseudah betoch haseudah einam te'unim bracha lo lifnehem velo achareihem?
Why did they say that things that come in the meal but
that are a part of the meal don't need a ברכה bracha
before and after? אמר להם הואיל ופת פוטרתן amar lahem ho'il upas
potartan because the bread exempts them. So the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי, I hachi, if that's true, by the way, even things that
require special ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona because they're a little not related
to the meal, pretty much everything is covered by the ברכת המזון.
Birchas Hamazon. So they said to him אי הכי, I hachi, if
that's true that the bread exempts them, יין נמי תיפטר בפת, yayin
nami tipater bepas, let
when you say המוציא, Hamotzi, let that even cover wine. And we're
taking it for granted, and we'll see in the next משנה, Mishna,
that assumes that when you have wine during the meal, you make
a בורא פרי הגפן. borei peri hagafen. Another הלכה halacha that people
are not aware of. It's not שבת, Shabbos, you didn't make קידוש,
kiddush, you're having a meal with bread, and then somebody brings... you
have to make a בורא פרי הגפן? Borei Pri Hagafen? Wine is
not covered with המוציא. Hamotzi. So he says, why not? That's מחמת
הסעודה. machmat haseudah. Surely it was a custom to drink wine as
a regular part of the meal, so say a בורא פרי הגפן?
Borei Pri Hagafen? So don't say בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen.
So גמרא Gemara says, שאני יין, shani yayin, wine is different, דגורם
ברכה לעצמו. d'goreim bracha l'atzmo. It causes a ברכה bracha for itself.
What does that mean? Well, it sounds a little like a tautology,
but anyway, what does it mean? So רש"י Rashi says what it
means is is that the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen is
a ברכה bracha that has status beyond ברכת הנהנין. birchas hanehenin. We
say it at קידוש, Kiddush, we say it at הבדלה, Havdalah, so
it's a type of a ברכה bracha that is also like a
ritual ברכה, bracha, it's not just a ברכת הנהנין birchas hanehenin ברכה.
bracha. And therefore בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen always has a
particular status, and even though somehow it's part of the meal, you
know, we want to give the status to בורא פרי הגפן, Borei
Pri Hagafen, we want to maintain that as a separate ברכה. bracha.
תוספות Tosafot says slightly different, or not slightly different, that בורא פרי
הגפן, Borei Pri Hagafen, like פת—this pas is probably a little more
intuitive—is the one thing in which you have a special ברכה bracha
because of the status of the object. Meaning, if בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Pri Hagafen really should have been בורא פרי העץ, borei pri
ha'etz, and פת pas really should have been בורא מיני מזונות, borei
minei mezonos, but because of the particular status of bread, we give
a special ברכה bracha to bread, המוציא. Hamotzi. And because of the
particular status of wine, we give a special ברכה bracha of wine,
a בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. Wine and bread are the
only two things that are not a class, but are a special
ברכה bracha for that particular food type itself, that one food type,
wine and bread. And because wine has that significance and that weight,
so therefore even when it comes in the middle of the meal,
we want to sort of give it that weight of the importance
of wine. So the importance of bread and the importance of wine
do not get overshadowed. Right, even if you knew you're having the
wine. Even if you knew, all of this is you knew you
were having it, right. It wasn't a separate question. Even though you
know you're going to have it, if you would make a בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen in the middle of a meal. Correct,
Mike's correct, even if you were planning on having it, it is
not covered by—wine does not get overshadowed. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says: רב הונא Rav Huna אכל תליסר ריפתא בני תלתא תלתא
בקבא. achal tlaysar rifti b'ney tlaysa tlaysa b'kava. רב הונא Rav Huna
ate thirteen like certain types of like cakes or
wafers and this is going to be פת הבאה בכיסנין. pas haba
b'kisnin. So we're going to discuss for a minute this very important
category of פת הבאה בכיסנין. pas haba b'kisnin. Let me read the
story and then I'll step back and discuss it. So he ate
a lot of them, thirteen of these cakes, of which three cakes
were a קב. kav. So they were pretty big cakes or wafers
or biscuits, and there were, you know, each one was pretty large
and he ate thirteen of them. ולא בירך, V'lo beirech, and he
didn't בירך, beirech, he didn't make the ברכה. bracha. Now obviously it
doesn't mean that he didn't make a ברכה bracha in the beginning,
but it meant that he didn't do a ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon.
Okay, sometimes in the גמרא Gemara it wants to say, you know,
you don't make a—you know, even though obviously it takes for granted
you make a בורא נפשות, borei nefashos, but in the—but in contrast
to ברכת המזון birchas hamazon it'll say you didn't make a ברכה
bracha afterwards, which means you didn't do a ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon.
אמר ליה רב נחמן, Amar lei Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said to רב הונא, Rav Huna, עדי כפנא, adai kafna, you
know, until, you know,
these are for these are for hunger. Or there's other ways of
reading this like rhetorical: Is this not for hunger? So basically this
wasn't just a snack. You ate thirteen of these. You filled yourself
up with these. So how could you not say ברכת המזון? birchas
hamazon? אלא הא הלכה, Ella ha halacha, but here's the הלכה: halacha:
כל שאחרים קובעים עליו סעודה צריך לברך. kol she'acherim kove'im alav seudah
tzarich l'vareich. If it's the normal amount that normal people would sit
down to a meal for this amount, even though it's a type
of a מזונות, mezonos, if you're קובע סעודה kove'a seudah on it,
if it's certainly if it's a פת הבאה בכיסנין pas haba b'kisnin
and you're קובע סעודה, kove'a seudah, you have to make a—you have
to do a ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. So what is this פת
הבאה בכיסנין? pas haba b'kisnin? We mentioned it before, that it was
a בורא מיני מזונות, borei minei mezonos, but again—and here we are
saying that it's a בורא מיני מזונות borei minei mezonos that can
sometimes become a ברכת המזון birchas hamazon when you are קובע סעודה,
kove'a seudah, or also by comparably presumably it would get a המוציא
Hamotzi as well in the beginning. Now what is—what is פת הבאה
בכיסנין? pas haba b'kisnin? So there are basically there really like five
positions in the ראשונים, Rishonim, but they're—let's talk about the three main
ones because they're very easy to relate to, which are technically you
know could be המוציא. Hamotzi. It's got flour, it's got water, you
bake it, but because it doesn't serve as bread, it gets more
of a מזונות mezonos status, but it could always go back into
being המוציא Hamotzi and ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. So what are these
three? They are—I'm going to tell you. Number one, the approach of
רש"י, Rashi, which seems to be like the dough is something that
is very sweet and has a lot of spices, maybe has egg
or fruit juices, that's the רמב"ם Rambam says, essentially cake, okay. It
could or maybe—cake though is a very like loose batter. Another example
would be for
example a croissant. You know, croissant, right, it's got flour, it's water,
whatever, it's המוציא, Hamotzi, but again, it's very very sweet and the
additives affect the taste of the dough itself. It's not really like
bread dough, not just because it could be loose, even if it's
not loose batter.
That's one example, but it's a type of a cake or very
sweet sweetened dough.
That's one approach of ראשונים Rishonim פת הבאה בכיסנין. pas haba b'kisnin.
Another approach is because of—they say from the word כיס kis like
a pocket, that it is some type of some type of a
dough that is filled filled essentially like a type of a pie
or a type of a, you know, what are the other things,
like a בורקס borekas or whatever. Although I'll talk about a meat
pie or בורקס borekas in a minute, a קניש, knish, you know,
some type of a thing like that. No, it's, you know, it's
baked dough or whatever, but it's again not functioning as bread. So
that's a type of a filled dough type of a thing, pie,
קניש, knish, etc. The third approach is, well let's see, we've covered
pie and cake. What's the other type of thing we say is
מזונות mezonos that's not bread? Pretzels. Pretzels, crackers. That's the third approach,
okay? So that's what רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel and other ראשונים Rishonim
say, which is it's a hard,
crunchy, thin, crunchy wafer type of a thing. Crackers, pretzels and so
on. Again, really have the same status, but possibly breadsticks and so
on. So those are the three general opinions. We tend to be
lenient like all of those and say בורא מיני מזונות Borei Minei
Mezonos and על המחיה, Al Hamichya, although some people say no, we
דוקא davka פסקן pasken one particular one. But the question becomes when
even if you פסקן pasken those categories does it really become a
type of a bread or like we've seen here a type of
a קביעת סעודה. keviyas seuda. So let me mention a couple of
relevant examples about this. Number one, the famous מזונות mezonos rolls. What
makes something a quote-unquote מזונות mezonos roll is that they do it
with like eggs, you know, they add some fruit juices or eggs
instead of with water. Now the point is, if you've ever eaten
those airline מזונות mezonos rolls, they taste totally like a normal roll.
So even those that say that it has to do with a
different sweetened dough and different tasting dough, it's not just technically you
have a little egg in there and it's all of a sudden
not המוציא. hamotzi. The dough there tastes the same and it tastes
like a loaf, tastes like normal bread, so it's, you know, it's
very, very questionable if you can make a מזונות mezonos on מזונות
mezonos rolls. Also, you're having it as normally you would have bread
in the meal, which is לכן קובעים עליו סעודה. lachen koveim alav
seuda. So מזונות mezonos rolls are highly questionable. Number one. Pizza, what?
What about חלה challah with raisins? חלה challah with raisins, the dough
is not affected. There's just something added into it, raisins, and that
doesn't really make it significant enough to make it different. You know,
there is a question at what stage does it taste like spiced
dough and at what stage does it taste like fundamentally a different
חלה. challah. I understand. So you know there's, right, it's sometimes hard
to draw those lines. There's a little שכל sechel here. It's a
lot of this has to do with, I think, intuitively we know
at a certain stage we're not thinking about things as bread, we're
thinking about them as functioning somehow else. But again, so you know,
so okay, so let me give you another... what? The appearance factor?
So appearance is a factor, that's not per se what's going on
here. That's called תריסא דנהמא, trisa de-anama, צורת לחם, tsuras lacham, which
we saw before. But it is worth mentioning that that is a
factor as well, but the primary definition here has to do with
these other qualities, not just appearance. So let me... pizza, for example.
Some people say פת הבאה בכיסנין, pas habah bikisnin, it's sort of
dough filled with something or its primary part of it is all
this other sort of stuff that you put on it. We could
also talk about meat קנישים knishes or meat pies. And here the
point is that at what stage is it if it's something that
is used as a primary part as as the meal. If you
would sit down to have a meal of meat pie, shepherd's pie,
whatever they call it, right? So maybe that sort of makes it
המוציא. hamotzi. Maybe the reason that a פת הבאה בכיסנין pas habah
bikisnin is a מזונות, mezonos, not המוציא, hamotzi, is because it always
serves as something in addition to the meal as a as some
type of a treat or whatever, snack, and not as a meal
itself. This case is a little bit more questionable because here it
might be that really the meat is the meal and this is
some type of secondary type of a thing. But by pizza, really
the pizza's the whole thing, it's like the and the crust is
the primary filler. And you know, so I don't know where people
think that pizza's a snack. I mean, you know, maybe they see
it's a late-night meal if you're hungry, but at least my sense
is that almost everybody, you know, pizza is a type of a
meal, not a huge meal but it's a meal. So certainly if
you're קובע סעודה, koveia seuda, but some would even argue it's not
even dependent on you in particular, you know, some will argue pizza's
always המוציא. hamotzi. Some say it's how much pizza you have, two
slices. I mean, I always make המוציא hamotzi on pizza. Breadsticks is
interesting because as well, breadsticks, if they're a type of a snack,
if you think about them, they're not really different than pretzels, right?
Same basic ingredient, we just call it breadsticks. So, but some people
do put out a bread basket and they don't have pretzels in
it, they have breadsticks in it, right? And maybe sometimes those are
used as a type of a similar function as bread and so
on. So it depends on your function there? Yes, so that's it
becomes a question, depends on you, depends... anyway, so these are the
three primary categories. As you can tell, the lines are going to
be hard to draw. But it's basically pies, pies, cakes, and and
crackers. That's a good way of thinking of the categories. But A
is the question in general at what stage are they used in
a way that makes them bread, and B even if they're used
in a way that they're a snack, here we see when you
do enough to be קובע סעודה koveia seuda on it, when it's
the quantity that becomes a קביעת סעודה, kviyas seuda, then it becomes
המוציא hamotzi and בורא מיני borei minei and and
ברכת המזון birkas hamazon and that's what we're looking. But enough being
defined as other people? Right, so just that, right, the גמרא Gemara
seems here like you go by this general consensus or standard. How
do you determine what the standard is, you know, how and whatever.
And what degree is the standard one way, but if you are
קובע סעודה koveia seuda even regardless of the standard maybe it's a...
Again, all these things are debated, but the point is that fundamentally
these things really do have the ingredients of bread, but because the
convention is they function in a non-bread-like way, they're מזונות mezonot and
על המחיה, al hamichya, but when even if the convention is that
because of the ingredients maybe they technically are in a category but
they still function as bread, like pizza might be a good example,
then that changes the ברכה bracha back to המוציא hamotzi or when
it's the quantity that makes it קביעות סעודה kveias seuda that would
also change the ברכה bracha back. Rifka, you had a question. Yeah,
it says he ate thirteen of these things and he didn't... ולא
בירך. velo beirech. It doesn't say he said על המחיה. al hamichya.
He didn't... so this seems to me to contradict the rules of
the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah says ואכלת ושבעת וברכת. veachalta vesavata
uverachta. Thirteen loaves, he was שבע, saveia, but because of the rabbis'
technical rules he avoided ואכלת ושבעת וברכת. veachalta vesavata uverachta. Yeah, that's
a good question. Now again, the גמרא, Gemara, you know, the גמרא
Gemara says ולא בירך velo beirech completely, but you know, רש״י Rashi
qualifies it and there are other גמרות Gemorot that... רש״י Rashi says
ולא בירך. velo beirech. רש״י Rashi says let's see,
רב הונא אכל תלתא... Rav Huna achal tlata... what? ולא בירך אחריו
velo beirech achrav at all. Yeah, okay, that's true, but there are
other גמרות... Gemorot... not... I understand. It's hard to imagine he didn't
say
על המחיה. al hamichya. Why didn't he say an על המחיה? al
hamichya? He ate a lot of מזונות. mezonot. I think that nor...
there are other cases I could show you, I can't sort of
pull them out right now, where the גמרא Gemara is clear that
the ולא בירך velo beirech doesn't mean not at all, it means
not the ברכה, bracha, you know, not the important ברכות. brachos. You
know, maybe he made a... maybe he made a בורא נפשות borei
nefashot or something. I understand, I understand. Okay, but I'm saying there
are other גמרות Gemorot that, you know, you have to interpret things
in context. But okay, I do understand the problem and you make
a good question, you know, because you could ask another thing. Let
me give you another thing. Let's say somebody filled themselves up with
a good meal of meat and potatoes and rice and all of
that, right? They wouldn't make a... they wouldn't do a ברכת המזון
Birkat Hamazon and, you know, and that would be ואכלת ושבעת. veachalta
vesavata. So I think that's a very good question. You know what,
let's hold off to when we get to because the next פרק
perek is about ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. Okay, discuss that. But the
question about how does the דרבנן d'rabbanan parameters of ברכת המזון Birkat
Hamazon fit with the דאורייתא d'oraisa concept of ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon,
and could you do... could you sort of not be doing the
דאורייתא d'oraisa is a good question. But let's hold off for the
next פרק perek on that. Yes. So what is the rule for
פת הבאה בכיסנין? pas haba bekisnin? Rule פת הבאה בכיסנין pas haba
bekisnin is מזונות mezonot and המוציא hamotzi and על המחיה. al hamichya.
If, however, it's a quantity which is normal קביעות סעודה, kveias seuda,
or the question what if you subjectively are קובע סעודה, koveia seuda,
but certainly if it's a normal quantity that leads to קביעות סעודה,
kveias seuda, then it's המוציא hamotzi and ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. If
it is a type of
a פת הבאה בכיסנין pas haba bekisnin that really is always used
as קביעות סעודה, kveias seuda, then it's not a פת הבאה בכיסנין
pas haba bekisnin anymore, then it's basically bread. You're saying like a
pizza? Pizza could be, I would think would be an example of
that. Good question. Yes. So according to רש״י Rashi it says כיסנין
kisnin is like some spiced bread so what does כיסנין kisnin mean?
I'm just trying to... I don't know. They... some people say it
means כיס, kis, to chew, I'm not sure. There's... not clear what
the etymology is. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, now we're going to say... so we didn't say פת הבאה
בכיסנין pas haba bekisnin there, but that seems implicit. And now the
גמרא Gemara is going to make it explicit. רב יהודה הוי עסיק
ליה לבריה בי רב יהודה בר חביבא. Rav Yehuda hava asik lei
l'vrie be Rav Yehuda bar Chaviva. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was
marrying off his son to the house of, meaning the daughter of,
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the son of חביבא. Chaviva. So they're having
a wedding party, or maybe they were in the middle of the
negotiations, whatever it was, they anyway, an engagement party, something. אייתו לקמייהו
פת הבאה בכיסנין. ayitu lekamaeihu pas haba bekisnin. So they brought in
front of them this type of a פת הבאה בכיסנין, pas haba
bekisnin, wafer, pie, cake, whatever it was, pizza. No, that's not a...
that's פת. pas. Anyway, they... כי אתא שמעינהו דקמברכי המוציא. ki ata
sham'inhu dekamvarchi hamotzi. So when... I'm sorry, אייתו לקמייהו, ayitu lekamaeihu,
they brought in front of the guests during this sort of let's
say engagement party this פת הבאה בכיסנין. pas haba bekisnin. So when
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda came into the room, he saw that everybody
was saying המוציא. hamotzi. כי אתא שמעינהו דקמברכי המוציא. ki ata sham'inhu
dekamvarchi hamotzi. אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to all the guests
there, מאי ציצי דקשמענא, mai tzi tzi dekashmana, what's this המוציא, hamotzi,
המוציא, hamotzi, המוציא, hamotzi, what's all this צי צי צי tzi tzi
tzi I'm hearing here? So he says, דילמא המוציא לחם מן הארץ
קמברכיתו, dilma hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz kamvarchitu, maybe you're making המוציא לחם
מן הארץ? hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz? אמרו ליה אין, amru lei in,
yes! דתני רב מונא אמר משום רב יהודה פת הבאה בכיסנין מברכין
עליו המוציא, detanya Rav Mona amar mishum Rav Yehuda pas haba bekisnin
mevorchin alav hamotzi, that even a פת הבאה בכיסנין pas haba bekisnin
you say המוציא. hamotzi. ואמר שמואל הלכה כרב מונא, veamar Shmuel halacha
keRav Mona, and שמואל Shmuel says the הלכה halacha is like רב
מונא, Rav Mona, we rule that way. אמר להו, amar lehu, so
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said to all these guests,
or whatever, maybe it's maybe it's also the people of the household
of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, whoever it was, anyway, אין הלכה כרב
מונא איתמר. ein halacha keRav Mona itmar. שמואל Shmuel said... he said
something about רב מונא, Rav Mona, but he said it's not like
רב מונא. Rav Mona. He didn't say it is like
רב מונא. Rav Mona. But one minute, we heard that you said
in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, לחמניות, lachmaniyos, which as the word
for like you know rolls, but again it's some other type of
a פת הבאה בכיסנין, pas habah bikisnin, so maybe it's you know
who knows some type of sweet rolls or something or you know
some type of a very flavored doughy thing. Well it's not a
simple roll. It's a פת הבאה בכיסנין, pas habah bikisnin, whatever that
is. מערבין בהו, me'arvin behu, you make use it for an עירוב
eruv when you need to sort of you know bring together a
couple of courtyards because to consider it as one if you have
the if you have the what do you call or you could
also use it as an עירוב eruv if you want to walk
outside the city. מערבין בהו מברכין עליהם המוציא. me'arvin behu mevar'chin aleihem
hamotzi. You say המוציא, hamotzi, it's considered bread and לחמניות lachmaniyos presumably
was understood to be in this פת הבאה בכיסנין pas habah bikisnin
category. So you yourself say that you say
המוציא. hamotzi. So so what did he say back? So שאני התם
דקבע סעודתא עלייהו. shani hasam d'kava sudasa aleihu. That's different because there
you're קובע סעודה koveia seuda on it. Now דקבע d'kava means in
a case where, it doesn't sound like that, it sounds like that
is a type of a פת הבאה בכיסנין pas habah bikisnin which
people use to be קובע סעודה koveia seuda on. So even if
technically it satisfies whatever the definition of פת הבאה בכיסנין pas habah
bikisnin is, if it's used as a type of a bread, if
it's used for קביעת סעודה, kvias seuda, then it has a המוציא
hamotzi regardless of if it satisfies those categories. It's no longer פת
הבאה בכיסנין pas habah bikisnin once it's functioning in that different way.
אבל היכא דלא קבע סעודתא עלייהו, aval heicha d'lo kava sudasa aleihu,
here it was just an engaging part, it was a little hors
d'oeuvres, so no, it's not a problem. For example, good question, right
the little franks in the blankets. Nobody is קובע סעודה koveia seuda
on that. Although I'm sure kids might, we love them. Okay. So
then no, I don't know about the kids. Whatever, that gets us
into a question about who you are anyway. But you would not
have to make המוציא, hamotzi, you could make a מזונות mezonos on
that. Okay. It does become a question, what about something that actually
started as המוציא, hamotzi, like bread chips. It didn't start as a
cracker, right, you know, they actually have bagel chips. Bagel chips and
those types of things. Although bagels has other issues because it's boiled
and then baked and so on. Anyway, so those are also those
are different types of questions. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. קבע סעודתא עלייהו. kava sudasa aleihu. ורב פפא איקלע
לבי רב הונא בריה דרב נתן. v'Rav Pappa ikla l'vei Rav Huna
brei d'Rav Noson. Rav Pappa dropped by the house of Rav Huna
the son of Rav Noson. בתר דגמרו סעודתייהו, basar d'gamru sudasaihu, after
they finished their meal, אייתו קמיהו מידי למיכל. aysu kameihu midi l'meichal.
So they brought out something to eat like a type of a
dessert. שקל רב פפא וקאכיל. shakal Rav Pappa v'ka-ochil. So Rav Pappa
sort of took and he ate it. He took it and he
ate it. אמרו ליה, amru leh, so they said to him, the
people of the house of Rav Huna.
This is very similar, right? Somebody's visiting and then the people of
the household sort of, he does a different practice and then the
people challenge or he challenges them. So anyway, so they said to
him, לא סבר ליה מר גמר אסור למיכל? lo savar leh mar
gamar assur l'meichal? Doesn't the master hold that after you're done with
the meal you can no longer eat anymore? Now what does this
mean no longer? It means until you bench. Now the ראשונים Rishonim
say that this doesn't mean it's אסור assur to eat, it means
it's אסור assur to eat without a ברכה. bracha. Okay? That if
you that when you're finished the meal anything now that you'll eat
is considered to be not connected to the meal and requires at
least a ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. Maybe even a ברכה אחרונה bracha
achrona according to the גמרא Gemara that you could have a real
state after fully after the meal where it would even get a
first and a last ברכה, bracha, something that you ate. But minimally
a ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. So the meal is over, it's not
connected, so it's forbidden to eat without a ברכה. bracha. So אמר
להו, amar lehu, so he said back to them, לא סליק איתמר.
lo salik itmar. It didn't say when you finish eating, it said
when you were סליק, salik, when you removed the table. So they
had these little personal tables next to them. So even if he
said, oh man, I'm full, I can't eat another bite and they
brought out some dessert, so everything, but
even if you say גמר, gamar, but if you haven't literally removed
the table, the meal isn't over yet and therefore you don't have
to make another ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. Now I will say that
I've interpreted this גמרא Gemara אסור למיכל assur l'meichal in the way
the ראשונים Rishonim do, that it's אסור assur unless you want to
make another ברכה. bracha. Of course then the question is, so what
was the whole challenge? Maybe he took the other piece and he
made a ברכה, bracha, right? And you know, what, you're not allowed
to eat? No, I made a ברכה. bracha. But you know, presume
you would have to explain the context, he took it without a
ברכה. bracha. But it is funny that it says אסור. assur. Why
is it אסור? assur? Let me make a ברכה bracha and continue
eating. Okay, and that is the way the ראשונים Rishonim say. So
now the question becomes when is the meal over that it requires
another ברכה? bracha? So let's take a look. גמר אסור
למיכל, gamar assur l'meichal, yeah, exactly, exactly. Well not עד שיברך ad
sheyivarech or אסור assur in the context was clear that it was
עד שיברך. ad sheyivarech. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say it explicitly. This
is what the ראשונים Rishonim read in because they want to figure
out why is it אסור, assur, you know, just make another ברכה.
bracha. So
anyway, so that now the question becomes when is the meal over
that it requires another ברכה? bracha? So let's take a look. Where
was it?
So this would be when you started doing? Yeah, well let's finish
the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. רבא רב זירא איקלעו לבי ריש גלותא. Rava Rav
Zeira iklu le-bei Reish Galuta. רבא Rava and רב זירא Rav Zeira
came to the house of the ריש גלותא, Reish Galuta, which was
the sort of political head, the Jewish political head in גלות. Galus.
ובתר דסליקו תכא, U-vatar de-saliku taka, so after they removed the plates
from there, so clearly it says סליקו, saliku, they removed the plates,
they removed everything. So מכמייהו
שדרו להו ריסתנא מבי ריש גלותא, mikamayeihu shadru le-hu ristanah mi-bei Reish
Galuta, they sent them some portion, it's interesting exactly what that word
means, but essentially they sent some final portion, some dessert from the
house of the ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. So they were maybe in
some other room, it was a castle, whatever it was, so you
know, they weren't, but then after they finished eating, they said, oh,
the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta says he wants you to have this
special here extra dish, okay, after they had removed their own dishes
and they thought they were done. So רבא אכל, Rava achal, רבא
Rava ate. רב זירא לא אכל, Rav Zeira lo achal, רב זירא
Rav Zeira didn't eat it. אמר ליה לא סבר ליה מר סילוק
אסור מלאכול? Amar lei lo savar lei mar siluk assur mi-le-echol? Don't
you hold that once you've removed the table you can't eat again,
presumably without a ברכה, bracha, but again, by context it sounds like
really אסור, assur, because if it was you could make a ברכה,
bracha, let them make a ברכה. bracha. But anyway, don't you hold
you're not allowed to eat after you remove the table? אמר ליה,
Amar lei, he said back to him, אנן אתכא דריש גלותא סמכינן.
Anan a-takka de-Reish Galuta samchinan. We are dependent on the, on the
plate of the ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. We're not finished until he's
finished. And therefore even if we say we're done, since we're eating
presumably, I don't exactly know whether he was eating in the same
room or not the same room, but somehow the meal isn't over
until he says it's over, okay, and the, right, it's not over
until it's over, until the fat lady sings, not over until the
ריש גלותא Reish Galuta finishes. So therefore even if we're done, he's
not done and it's still considered in the meal. That's the simple
sense of what it means. But I should say very important הלכה
halacha that emerges from here that ראשונים Rishonim understand, it's not just
a question of when the meal is over, but it's a question
about if you're a guest at somebody's house that
you assume, you don't know what you're going to be eating and
what you're not going to be eating, what they're going to be
bringing in front of you and not bringing in front of you.
So it's always assumed that you're making a ברכה bracha על דעת
בעל הבית, al da'at ba'al ha-bayit, on the,
based on the plans of the בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit or בעלת
הבית. ba'alat ha-bayit. So therefore they brought you this beautiful appetizer and
it was I don't know, some fish, and you made a שהכל,
shehakol, and you in your mind thought that the המוציא hamotzi was
coming next. And then they say, wait, now we have the second
appetizer and they bring you something else. So you don't have to
make another שהכל shehakol because you're על דעת בעל הבית, al da'at
ba'al ha-bayit, you know it's going to be what the בעל הבית
ba'al ha-bayit serves you and therefore whatever ברכה bracha you're making is
assumed to sort of be channeled through what their plans are, not
what your plans are. So if you take a look for example
in תוספות, Tosafot, he says, who was it? אה, אנן אתכא דריש
גלותא סמכינן. Anan a-takka de-Reish Galuta samchinan. תוספות Tosafot says, וכשרגילין לאכול
מיני פירות ומביאים
להם
זה אחר זה, U-keshe-regilin le-echol minei peirot u-mevi'im la-hem zeh achar zeh,
you know they bring you different fruit, you know you the, the
hosts bring you. יש אומרים שצריך לברך על כל חד וחד שאין
יודעים אם יתנו להם בעל הבית יותר. Yesh omrim she-tzarich le-vareich al
kol chad ve-chad she-ein yod'im im yitnu la-hem ba'al ha-bayit yoter. You
don't know if you're going to get more, so you're not planning
for more. ונראה שאין צריך לברך לפי שסומכים על שולחן בעל הבית
והיינו דבי ריש גלותא. Ve-nireh she-ein tzarich le-vareich le-fi she-somchim al shulchan
ba'al ha-bayit ve-hainu de-bei Reish Galuta.
And that's way he פוסק, poseks, very important הלכה halacha that you're
in somebody's house and they're feeding you, that, you know, that it
sort of now the question is exactly what the context is. You
know, let's say you're not sitting down to a meal, you're going
to somebody's house to do something and they offer you, you know,
a beer, and like two hours later or whatever, well then you
could start talking about סילוק דעת, siluk da'at, but you know there
you are, you're watching the ballgame or something, offered a beer and
then a little bit later, you know, you want to go eat
something else. Is that על דעת בעל הבית? al da'at ba'al ha-bayit?
You know, what's sort of the context? The simple context here is
that you're being fed by the בעל הבית. ba'al ha-bayit. That's the
context and therefore it all goes on what they are planning.
Yeah, so a question about being my own בעל הבית. ba'al ha-bayit.
Exactly. Yes,
so being your own בעל הבית ba'al ha-bayit doesn't work because then
you, that's the whole point, normally it goes by your דעת da'at
for yourself, right? So it's only when you're not in the position
to decide what you're going to be eating that you could say
your ברכה bracha is dependent on the other person. But when you
are, when you're just, I don't know, you're sort of foraging in
the fridge and you make a ברכה bracha now and then 20
minutes later you get hungry again and you go foraging again, but
that's your own דעת da'at because so you, you can't say, oh,
I'm going to depend, I'm going to base on whatever I future
decide will be included. You can't do that. That goes on what
you had in mind, you know, if you had in mind in
advance. Right, exactly, open-ended. No, what you could say is you could
say, I'm making a ברכה bracha on the whole fridge. Yeah, on
the whole fridge. Yeah,
that's an interesting question. Is it going to be sort of like
that generic? You know, how big of a group could it be?
I'm making a שהכל shehakol on like any food I might have
in the house. That's an interesting question. But you could certainly have
it to be including like a range of different stuff in mind,
you know, but I'll get back to you on like can it
be totally generic. Like you're not even thinking of the food, I
don't even know what I've got in my fridge, but I'm just
making a שהכל shehakol on anything I
decide. Are we not done? Let's keep on going. אמר רב. Amar
Rav. So we're not done with when the meal is over. אמר
רב: Amar Rav: הרגיל בשמן שמן מעכבו. haragil beshemen shemen me'akvo. So
if you normally wash your hands with oil after the meal because
they were smelly or whatever, didn't always have
hot running water and soap, so they would often put oil on
their hands afterwards. If you do that, שמן מעכבו. shemen me'akvo. So
the oil holds you back, meaning in a good way, means you're
not done yet with the meal until you've done this oil washing.
אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi: כי הוינא בי רב כהנא, ki
havina bei Rav Kahana, when I was in the house of רב
כהנא, Rav Kahana, אמרי
לן, amrei lan,
he said to us, excuse me, he said to us, כגון אנן
דרגילנא במשחא משחא מעכב לן, kegon anan deragilna bemishcha mishcha me'akev lan,
us that we have the custom to do the oil, משחא מעכב
לן, mishcha me'akev lan, the oil holds us back. And now the
גמרא Gemara concludes, right? ולית הלכתא ככל הני שמעתתא. V'leit hilchata kechol
hani shema'teta.
We don't rule like any of those opinions, either you say you're
done or you remove the table or the oil, none of that.
Why?
אלא כי הא דאמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, Ella ki
ha de'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Ashi amar Rav, here is what we
say: שלש תכופות הן, shalosh techofot hen, there are three immediates. תכף
לסמיכה שחיטה, tachef lismicha shechita, right after you do סמיכה smicha you
slaughter the animal. תכף לגאולה תפילה, tachef ligeula tefila,
right after you say גאל ישראל Gaal Yisrael you
דאוון. daven. And תכף לנטילת ידים ברכה, tachef lintilat yadayim bracha, and
right after you do נטילת ידים netilat yadayim you make the ברכה.
bracha. Now why these three? There are other things that are תכף,
tachef, but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi has a פסוק pasuk for all of
these, which might be why they were quoted as a group. Now
what נטילת ידים? netilat yadayim? It could be the נטילת ידים netilat
yadayim before. You wash your hands and then you say על נטילת
ידים, al netilat yadayim, that makes a lot of sense. Here it's
understanding it to be the נטילת ידים netilat yadayim at the end,
that is then right ברכה, bracha, the מים אחרונים mayim acharonim which
here presumably is not based on מלח סדומית melach sdomit or other
things. Here it just seems to be like the oil that everybody
washes their hands at the end and that defines the end. And
therefore right after you have to make a ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon.
So now let's finish it. אמר אביי אף אנן נימא. Amar Abaye
af anan neima. So, you know what? Let's add one. תכף לתלמידי
חכמים ברכה. tachef letalmidei chachamim bracha. At the right after
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim comes a blessing. Not exactly the same תכף,
tachef, but it immediately follows the presence of a תלמיד חכם. talmid
chacham. שנאמר ויברכני ה' בגללך. shene'emar vayivarcheni Hashem biglalecha.
God has blessed me because of you. What Laban said to Yaakov.
Interesting now, Yaakov being cast as the תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Excuse
me, Laban said to Yaakov, Laban being cast as the... I mean
no. Yaakov being cast as the תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. אי בעית
אימא מהכא, ei bayit eima mehacha, or from here, שנאמר ויברך ה'
את בית המצרי בגלל יוסף. shene'emar vayevarech Hashem et beit hamitzri biglal
Yosef.
Yosef came into the house and it was blessed. Again, doesn't really
fit the idea of תכף. tachef. Also a little funny thinking about
Yaakov and Yosef as תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that wouldn't be the
exact normal sort of category I'd put them in, you know, צדיקים,
tzaddikim, מעלות, ma'alot, it's a different thing. Anyway, that's what he adds.
Nice sort of little אגדתא agadata to end. Now in terms of
the ברכות, brachot, so for so important issue is again, ראשונים rishonim
earlier said that it didn't really mean אסור, assur, it really meant
that if you want to make another ברכה bracha you could make
another ברכה. bracha. However, when the גמרא Gemara here speaks about
תכף, tachef, תכף לנטילת ידים ברכה, tachef lintilat yadayim bracha,
תוספות Tosafot seems to indicate, and the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah and
the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch certainly seem to indicate, and the משנה
ברורה Mishnah Berurah reinforces this, that even if you wanted to make
a ברכה bracha you shouldn't. After you do מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim,
you have to... you should right away בענטש, bench, you shouldn't talk,
you certainly shouldn't talk and other types of things. And even if
you wanted to eat another thing you should make a ברכה. bracha.
Now some disagree, ערוך השולחן Aruch HaShulchan if memory serves, says what's
the big... and the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah sort of recognizes that
there's this position out there. What's the big deal? So make another
מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. I understand מים אחרונים mayim acharonim has to
come right before בענטשינג, benching, but if you want to talk or
eat some more or make another ברכה, bracha, do all of that
and then do מים אחרונים mayim acharonim again and then have it
right before, you know, right before the בענטשינג. benching. This won't be...
you didn't make a ברכה bracha on it, okay? But some disagree,
some say when you do it with the intent of מים אחרונים,
mayim acharonim, you have to בענטש bench right away. No talking, no
what, even if you want to do another מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim.
Okay, now that's assuming that we do מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. People
nowadays don't do מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim, so things would change. But
even I will say personally, even when I was doing מים אחרונים,
mayim acharonim, which I don't do anymore, I went like ערוך השולחן.
Aruch HaShulchan. Like you know, although the simple sense of the... תכף
tachef was from... make the other thing the מים אחרונים mayim acharonim
if you want to talk, you want to make a ברכה bracha
and so on. Let's see... terms would be like... would be like
גמרא, Gemara, wouldn't be like... well the question is nowadays that we
don't have מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim, what constitutes the end nowadays? And
it might be it goes more to things like גמרא, Gemara, it
might not even require סילוק silluk because we don't have little personal
personal trays in front of us, but it might be taking the
plates away, clearing off the table. So those questions, yes, they are
you know, still remain. Exactly. But what about then? I'm not giving
an answer today. Yes, but yes, it's possible. My answer is it's
possible. There's a question of exactly where to draw the line if
you're not נוהג noheg in מים אחרונים, mayim acharonim, yes. If you
decide to stop eating? Well,
that's not for now. Okay, so I'm not clear why it makes
a matter a difference in הלכה halacha when it's considered the end.
What? I'm not clear why it makes a difference what when it's
considered גמר סעודה. gemar seudah. Because then, because the thing that exempts
you from the ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona of other food is they're
considered part of the meal. If you have basically designated through words
and actions that the meal is over, then if you eat something
else, it's not being eaten as part of the meal. It's being
eaten as something after the meal, so therefore it gets another ברכה.
bracha. Okay. Yeah, I mean
there are different communities that it's much more common. Yeah, and in
more חרדי charedi communities it's much more common, but when we get
to a discussion of מים אחרונים mayim acharonim we can discuss it.
Okay.
Yeah, but we encounter like the dessert could be a separate ברכה
bracha anyway.
Right. So the concept of our meal... Yeah, but you could say
something, you know, let me let me just get a little bit
more of that of that beef before we bentch. You know, you
could have a case where it's not dessert, you want to חאפ
chap something more from the meal and it's still a relevant question.
But then I would think that if you if you have something
on which you make a separate ברכה bracha as a dessert, then
you're still... It might be a moot point anyway. Yeah, that's true.
That's true. But there could be cases where it's not a dessert
and the question and you still have to decide is the meal
over or not. Okay, let's say you want to keep on eating
bread. You know, you want another piece of bread before you bentch.
Okay.
Now the גמרא gemara continues. By the way, I should point out
that תוספות Tosafot is bothered by the idea that they would remove
the table before bentching because he says it's דווקא davka our practice
to keep the table, presumably the idea of keeping bread on the
table before bentching. And תוספות Tosafot says yeah, that's when they had
private tables, but for us, you know, we remove people's plates but
we still keep, you know, the bread on the table. And also
what? Yeah, okay. Anyway, so now let's take a look.
Yeah, I know, I know. I'm just trying to remind myself of
one other point I wanted to make about תוספות. Tosafot. Yeah, תוספות
Tosafot makes another two other points though interesting about halachic status of
things as defining them as part of the meal. He wants to
make say why we don't say a בורא פרי האדמה borei pri
ha'adamah when we have מרור. maror. Because you know, normally you wouldn't
have מרור maror as מחמת הסעודה machmat haseudah to fill you, whatever,
you know, why don't we say בורא פרי האדמה borei pri ha'adamah
when we have מרור? maror? So he says because since the הלכה
halacha demands that it be eaten in that place, that defines it
as part of the סעודה, seudah, even if it does not function
to serve the filling function. Then he gives an example, let's say
you, you know, you said, you did סילוק השולחן siluk hashulchan or
whatever you did and then you're on סדר Seder night and you
realize you didn't eat the אפיקומן. afikoman. Okay. So he says the
fact that הלכה halacha demands that you eat the אפיקומן, afikoman, it's
sort of like the same way you say you're סומך על דעת
בעל הבית, someich al da'at ba'al habayis, you say you're סומך על
דעת הקדוש ברוך הוא someich al da'at hakadosh baruch hu or the
דעת ההלכה. da'at hahalacha. And therefore since הלכה halacha demands it, so
it's never like you had you really haven't defined yourself as finishing
because הלכה halacha would have demanded that you also do this. So
that's interesting when there's a halachic requirement, how that might define the
parameters of the meal. When it comes to since it's coming up
to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah should just mention, of course, when it
comes to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that's the question of do you
make the העץ ha'eitz on the fruit? You know, it's not exactly
a הלכה, halacha, it's a מנהג minhag to do the העץ. ha'eitz.
It's certainly not מחמת הסעודה. machmat haseudah.
So some people are always to play things safe and have a
little bread with it. I make a העץ, ha'eitz, I think it's
clearly not מחמת הסעודה. machmat haseudah. It's not like
תוספות's Tosafot's case about מרור maror and things like that. Then we
come to the question of when do you say the שהחיינו shehecheyanu
before or after the בורא פרי העץ? borei pri ha'eitz? So I
get out of it because you can make a שהחיינו shehecheyanu not
only when you eat a new fruit but when you see a
new fruit. So I'll look at the fruit, say a שהחיינו shehecheyanu
and then I'll say a ברכה. bracha. But you've seen it before
then? What? Even though you've seen it before then? Yeah, but you
know, there's a period you don't and that's the first even if
you missed it the first second and the first opportunity.
So the other thing you could do is you could make a
העץ ha'eitz on the apple and have the apple first, העץ, ha'eitz,
and then you don't make the שהחיינו shehecheyanu and that includes all
the fruit you're going to be bringing out and then you make
the שהחיינו shehecheyanu on the fruit. Okay. Now the גמרא gemara continues.
Next משנה. mishnah.
בירך על
היין שלפני המזון פטר את היין שלאחר המזון. Beirach al hayayin shelifnei
hamazon patar es hayayin she'achar hamazon. If you made a ברכה bracha
on the wine, they used to have they would drink then they
would bring out the bread, but they'd have, you know, some hors
d'oeuvres, some drinking, bring out the bread, have their nice meal, then
wrap up the meal and then of course have some more drinking
and some more post-meal hors d'oeuvres and some more little snacks at
the end of the meal. Is this about זימון? zimun? No, this
is about זימון. zimun. So בירך על היין, Beirach al hayayin, so
you made the ברכה bracha on the wine, the pre-meal wine. פטר
את היין שלאחר המזון. Patar es hayayin she'achar hamazon. That includes exempts
the wine you're going to have post-meal, again, even though the meal
will be over and it'll be like a post-meal drinking and snacking.
And the pre-wine isn't קידוש Kiddush either? No, no, it's a normal
thing. בירך על הפרפרת שלפני המזון. Beirach al haparperes shelifnei hamazon. If
you made a ברכה bracha on the snack and presumably this was
some type of a מזונות mezonos snack before the meal. פטר את
הפרפרת שלאחר המזון. Patar es haparperes she'achar hamazon. It covers the snack
after the meal. Again, even though these are not covered by the
המוציא, Hamotzi, wine is never covered by המוציא, Hamotzi, and anyway these
aren't covered because they're either before or after the meal. The
one of the ברכות brachos can cover the other even though there's
a long period of time between them. So the question about dessert
also? Right.
Right. So then it does become question, right, how long of a
time? I mean, certainly if it's about the meal, but like some
ראשונים Rishonim say why doesn't the מרור maror or the בורא פרי
האדמה Borei Pri Ha'adamah of the כרפס karpas cover? And some say
it does and you should have it in mind, but תוספות Tosfos
says no, such a הפסק hefsek with the הגדה Hagaddah and the
meal and all those things. Well, maybe the הגדה's Hagaddah a הפסק,
hefsek, but here you have—you see before and after the meal, it's
all stays loosely connected, so at least it's considered that the ברכה
bracha before can extend even to the end after. So yes, your
point about making, you know, the העץ ha'eitz at one point covering
a later point is a good one. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, or the משנה Mishnah says,
ברך על הפת—if berach al hapos you make a ברכה bracha on
the bread—פטר את הפרפרת, poter es haparperes, it exempts the snacks, presumably
the snacks even afterwards, which is an interesting question: didn't we just
say that the stuff that comes at the end for a type
of a dessert
is—is not covered by the המוציא? Hamotzi? So תוספות Tosfos tries to
say that these snacks are really, you know, fundamentally some type of
bread chips and it really isn't like מזונות, mezonos, it really is
a type of bread and it's not a—and it is a המוציא,
Hamotzi, it's not a מזונות. mezonos. And that's why that it's covered
even, you know, even by the—even though it comes after the meal,
it's covered by the המוציא. Hamotzi. Okay, על הפרפרת, al haparperes, if
you make a ברכה bracha though on these פרפרת, parperes, לא פטר
את הפת, lo poter es hapos, it does not exempt the bread,
presumably it is—even though according to תוספות Tosfos it's both a possibly
המוציא, Hamotzi, but it's not significant enough and it is considered to
be like not enough to really exempt real bread. בית שמאי אומרים,
Beis Shammai omrim, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says, אף לא מעשה קדרה,
af lo ma'aseh kdeirah, even not sort of pot food. We'll see
what that means in the גמרא, Gemara, גמרא Gemara has a question
how to interpret בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Now continues: היו יושבין, hayu
yoshvin, if they were sitting down, כל אחד מברך לעצמו, kol echad
mevarech le'atzmo, then each person has to make any ברכה ראשונה bracha
rishona for themselves, whether it's bread or other food, you make your
own ברכה. bracha.
הסבו, heseivu, אחד מברך לכולן. echad mevarech lekulan. If, however, they reclined,
so they're really being קובע סעודה koveiah seudah together, then one person
makes for everybody. Now this is interesting, right? We, you know, normally
obviously we know you don't make a ברכת הנהנין birchas hane'enin for
somebody else, you make it for yourself. But why not make it
for somebody else as long as you're also deriving benefit? Why don't
we say שומע כעונה? shomei'a ke'oneh? There is a real disinclination to
apply שומע כעונה shomei'a ke'oneh for ברכת הנהנין birchas hane'enin and ברכת
המזון birchas hamazon because this is about your personal subjective experience of
getting benefit and therefore it demands your personal ברכה, bracha, not you
to be responsive to somebody else's ברכה, bracha, which basically is expressing
their thanks. It has to be you and your—and you're just piggybacking.
It has to be fundamentally you expressing your acknowledgment, your thanks. When
do we allow you to be יוצא? yotzei? When we define you
as a group. And then somebody is making for the group. It's
not that somebody is making for himself and you're piggybacking. You're all
a group and this person is expressing the ברכה bracha of the
group. And that's the idea of זימון zimmun at the end, where
there's an institution—one person did the בענטשן bentching for everybody because it
was a group. And here the idea as well for the beginning
ברכות brachos of הסבו. heseivu. That when they all reclined and not
just all come to a cafeteria table together and they happen to
be eating next to one another, but they're all קובע סעודה koveiah
seudah together, then it's a group and then one person can make
a ברכה bracha for the group. Now the question is what constitutes
nowadays הסבו? heseivu? On the one hand, we don't even have הסבה,
haseibah, so you could say so therefore we never get it, or
you could say we don't need it. It's not what defines קביעות
סעודה kvi'us seudah for us. So תוספות Tosfos says yes, הסבה haseibah
doesn't define קביעות סעודה, kvi'us seudah, but we would never say that
we're קובע סעודה koveiah seudah together without bread. That's at least what
תוספות Tosfos says. So for המוציא, Hamotzi, you can make—that's what we
do every שבת. Shabbos. Okay, but תוספות Tosfos says that we would
never consider something קביעות סעודה kvi'us seudah without bread. Now you could
question that. Why isn't it contextual? And nowadays plenty of times people
sit together for a meal and they say we're all get together
for a meal and there's no bread there. Okay, but anyway, this
is not the most pressing question. Mostly we don't have—most people don't
need somebody else to be מוציא motzi them in a ברכה ראשונה.
bracha rishona. But that does become the question, what for us constitutes
הסבו, heseivu, the type of reclining and קביעות סעודה kvi'us seudah to
make it a group that one person can make the ברכה. bracha.
So now the משנה Mishnah continues, yes—but what if it's just one
other person? It would be the same thing. Right, right, right. It
would be the same thing.
It's not like a זימון zimmun that you need three, this idea,
correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: בא להם
יין בתוך המזון, ba lahem yayin betoch hamazon, now wine came in
the middle of the meal, כל אחד ואחד מברך לעצמו, kol echad
ve'echad mevarech le'atzmo, then everybody then the drinking of the wine in
a meal is considered independent. I'm drinking my wine because I'm thirsty
and you're drinking your wine or you're not or you're drinking your
water or whatever, we're not drinking as a group. Okay? We're eating
maybe as a group, we're not drinking as a group. By the
way, this makes it clear that you have to make a בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen with wine in the middle of a
meal, okay, which is the assumption the גמרא Gemara had before. אבל
לאחר המזון, aval le'achar hamazon, if after we're done we all bring
out a bottle of wine to share, then we're drinking together. Right?
During the meal we're eating together and we're drinking alone, but after
the meal we could be drinking together. And therefore one
person—anyway—right, and therefore one person can make the ברכה bracha for everyone.
אחד מברך לכולן. echad mevarech lekulan. והוא אומר על המוגמר. Vehu omer
al hamugmar. They would have a practice also, we're gonna find out
sort of second century ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael eating practices pretty soon,
so they would bring out incense afterwards and they would burn incense
and there would be like an incense thing and the aroma would
come and everybody would sort of smell from this incense pot or,
it's not a pot whatever it would be anyway, and it's one
person who would make the ברכה. beracha. So they would do that
after ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon. So it says the guy that you
gave the כבוד, kavod, this is not like הלכתית halachically it has
to, but this is more דרך ארץ derech eretz or what the
practice was, the guy you gave the כבוד kavod to make the
בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen on the post-meal drinking, makes the
ברכה beracha on the בשמים besamim on the burning of the incense
after the meal. ואף על פי שמביאים את המוגמר אלא אחר סעודה,
Ve'af al pi shemevi'im et hamugmar ela achar se'udah, even though that
comes even after everything, maybe even after the בנצ'ן, benching, nevertheless the
practice was whoever made the ברכה beracha on the drinking afterwards makes
also makes that ברכה. beracha. דאיתמר עלה. De'itamar alah. There you go.
So let's take a look now what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbah bar bar Channah
amar Rabbi Yochanan. לא שנו אלא בשבתות ובימים טובים. Lo shanu ela
beshabbatot uveyamim tovim. This idea that the wine before exempts the wine
after, that's only on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov. Why?
הואיל ואדם קובע סעודתו על היין. Ho'il ve'adam kove'a se'udato al hayayin.
Because on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב, Yom Tov, therefore you, you
know, the practice is that after the meal is over you sit
together and you drink wine together. אבל בשאר ימות
השנה מברך על כל כוס וכוס. Aval bish'ar yemot hashanah mevarech al
kol kos vekhos. Afterwards, at other times during the year, it's not
like you know that there's wine coming, and every another glass of
wine is a new decision to drink wine, and therefore you have
to make a separate ברכה beracha for each one. So this is
quite fascinating because obviously it's not פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishnah.
You know, first you wonder well, maybe it's a difference between ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל, Bavel, but this is in the name
of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, so it's ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But
okay, you know, maybe it was also different from the time the
משנה Mishnah was written to the time of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
But he's basically saying nowadays we don't sit and drink together after
the meal. So therefore nowadays even if you make a בורא פרי
הגפן Borei pri hagafen before, every decision on a new כוס kos
of wine is a new ברכה. beracha. Now of course you could
have a different of the extreme, you could say maybe we don't,
you know, maybe we don't drink after the meal, but
maybe another כוס kos during the meal we would have had in
mind. But this is the question also about what is in mind,
and if it wasn't in mind you have to make a new
ברכה beracha and he assumes generally it's not in mind. So the
גמרא Gemara says: איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, this was also taught. אמר
רבה בר מרי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי לא שנו אלא בשבתות
ובימים טובים ובשעה. Amar Rabbah bar Mari amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
lo shanu ela beshabbatot uveyamim tovim uvshata. Now here so you don't
think it's somehow linked to קידוש, Kiddush, so he adds other
things. ובשעה שאדם יוצא מבית המרחץ ובשעה שהקיז דם. Uvshata she'adam yotzei
mibeit hamerchatz uvshata shehikiz dam. After you've gone to for a שוויץ
shvitz or after you do bloodletting, then people would sit together and
drink wine. So then if you make on one ברכה beracha on
one כוס kos of wine, you know you're going to be drinking
a lot of wine now. That was the practice to drink a
lot of wine. הואיל
ואדם קובע סעודתו על היין. Ho'il ve'adam kove'a se'udato al hayayin. Because
then you're sitting down drinking a lot of wine. So once you
do one בורא פרי הגפן Borei pri hagafen it accounts for all
the wine you're going to be drinking. אבל בשאר ימות השנה, Aval
bish'ar yemot hashanah, other times during the year, מברך על כל כוס
וכוס, mevarech al kol kos vekhos, you make it on every כוס
kos because you normally are not just because you're having one glass,
you're not necessarily planning on having the next glass. Now the question
always is, is this like the default? If I specific, maybe it's
a default I'm not thinking סתם, stam, what do we assume the
norm is? But, so you know, in some context the norm is
to be drinking, so even if you weren't particularly thinking about it
we'll assume that's included, other cases the norm is not, so we'll
assume it's not. But what happens if I specifically have intent in
a way that's opposite the norm? So we'll see one example of
that right now. Let's take a look. רבה בר מרי, Rabbah bar
Mari, רבה בר מרי איקלע לבי רבא בחול. Rabbah bar Mari ikla
lebei Rava bechol. So רבה בר מרי Rabbah bar Mari came to
רבא's Rava house in the weekday. חזי דבריך לפני המזון והדר בריך
לאחר המזון. Chazi devarich lifnei hamazon vehadar barich le'achar hamazon. He made
the ברכה beracha on wine beforehand and then he made another ברכה
beracha on wine after. אמר ליה יישר. Amar lei yeyasher. He said
to him יישר. Yeyasher. So יישר כח Yeyasher koach is already in
the
גמרא. Gemara. יישר כחך, Yeyasher koachaka, like good going. וכן אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי. Vekhen amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. You know what?
What you said is also what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi said that nowadays the ברכה beracha on wine one כוס
kos doesn't cover the end of the meal because we normally aren't
planning planning that as what's going to follow. Right, well let's take
a look. רב יצחק איקלע לבי אביי. Rav Yitzchak ikla lebei Abaye.
רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak came to the house of אביי. Abaye. ביום
טוב, Beyom tov, it was יום טוב. Yom Tov. חזי דבריך אכל
כסא וכסא. Chazi devarich akol kassa vekhassa. And he made a ברכה
beracha on every כוס kos of wine, glass of wine. אמר ליה
לא סבר ליה מר להא דרבי יהושע בן לוי? Amar lei lo
savar lei mar leha deRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi? Doesn't the master hold
what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi teaches, that on
שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov we're planning on drinking, so
therefore it's all included? אמר ליה נמלך אנא. Amar lei nimlach ana.
No, I, I changed my mind. I know most people plan on
drinking, I figured I was going to take it easy this יום
טוב, Yom Tov, then I was having such a good time I
decided to join in. Okay, but since initially though I was not
planning, therefore it does not include. So again the question is how
much, so here is it because I specifically had in mind I
wasn't going to? You know, what sort of is the default and
so on, and also here we have where you're deciding you thought
you weren't going to, then it requires another ברכה beracha because then
it wasn't in your mind and it wasn't the default or whatever.
But what happens if, you know, you had in mind... Actually you
do, you know, well, going to a bar is like the גמרא
Gemara about coming out of a שוויץ, shvitz, you know, where דווקא
davka you're קובע koveia on יין. yayin. But let's say, you know,
nowadays, you know, we're sitting down for a meal and I am
planning to have a good couple of glasses of wine, and I'm
planning to drink afterwards, and it's the weekday and it's not יום
טוב Yom Tov or whatever. Presumably that can cover me, right? Presumably
these things, as we see, are sort of default assumptions, but specific
contexts where those things are different, שבת, Shabbos, יום טוב, Yom Tov,
bar, whatever, or maybe times when my דעת da'as is different would
change some of these default assumptions. Okay, so now let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes. איבעיא
להו, Iba'alu, they raised a point question: באו להם יין בתוך המזון
מהו שיפטור היין שלאחר המזון? ba'u lahem yayin betoch hamazon mah she-yiftar
hayayin sheleachar hamazon? How about wine during? We're talking about the wine
that's drunk before, afterwards, about drinking, as we found out at the
end of the משנה, Mishnah, the wine you would drink during wouldn't
be about sitting together and drinking together, it would just be about
washing down your food. So is the ברכה bracha of בורא פרי
הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen on the wine during the meal, can that
count for the wine after, even presumably if you were planning on
drinking wine after? So here we see it's not all based on
דעת. da'as. If somehow categorically we defined this as a different type
of a drinking, and maybe also because one is during the meal
and one's after the meal, then it cannot be covered even presumably
if you had it in mind, or that seems to be the
case. So let's take a look. Yes, but why what the בעל
הבית Baal HaBayis just said? Yeah, it seems to me that all
of these questions really relate to what is the default for, you
know, for the people who are speaking, right? Not what is the
objective rule. Right, but that's why up until now, I agree, up
until now it could all have been sort of what's your דעת
da'as or what's your sort of like norm of practice, so it
becomes your סתם. stam. But this question is a more rule-based because
here it's not a question about whether you will be drinking wine
after, whether it's in your mind after. Here was a question about
whether
qualitatively wine during the meal connects to, which is about washing down
food, connects to wine after. Now you could say maybe the point
is that since they're qualitatively different, I'm not thinking about the wine
after the meal when I'm focusing on the wine during the meal.
But it does seem here to be a little bit different than
the others, it's not related to the דעת da'as question. Let's see
what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. It
says: רב אמר פוטר, Rav amar poter, it does exempt you. רב
כהנא אמר אינו פוטר, Rav Kahana amar eino poter, רב כהנא Rav
Kahana says no. רב נחמן אמר פוטר. Rav Nachman amar poter. רב
ששת אמר אינו פוטר. Rav Sheshet amar eino poter. רב הונא ורב
יהודה וכל תלמידי דרב
אמרי אינו פוטר. Rav Huna ve-Rav Yehuda ve-chol talmidei de-Rav amri eino
poter.
All the students of רב Rav said it does not exempt you.
There are fundamentally different types of drinking, so the ברכה בורא פרי
הגפן bracha Borei Pri Hagafen on one during does not exempt the
other. And this does seem that this is clearly not just a
question of דעת, da'as, but a question of somehow category and connect.
Now if it was both during the meal maybe it wouldn't be
such a problem, but because you're trying to connect the drinking during
with drinking after, maybe they have to be also somewhat of the
same type, of the same category.
Let's just finish the two dots. So it says, איתיבי רב לרב
נחמן. Eisevei Rav le-Rav Nachman.
So רב Rav asked רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. באו להם יין בתוך
המזון, ba'u lahem yayin betoch hamazon, our משנה Mishnah says when the
wine came during the meal, כל אחד ואחד מברך לעצמו, kol echad
ve-echad mevarech le-atzmo, then you make your own ברכה. bracha. לאחר המזון
אחד מברך לכולם. le-achar hamazon echad mevarech lekulam. Because everybody is drinking
by themselves, you know, conceptually by themselves, they're not drinking together. And
then when it came after the meal, אחד מברך לכולם. echad mevarech
lekulam. And he assumes this was the same meal. So it says
you made a ברכה bracha during and one made for everybody, and
then you brought the wine after and now one can make for
every and now one, I mean, you went during and each person
makes for himself, then you brought the wine after and one person
makes for every. So here you see they made a ברכה bracha
during and they still had to make a ברכה bracha after. So
that should prove that side of the debate. אמר ליה הכי קאמר.
amar lei hachi ka'amar.
No, that's not what the משנה Mishnah is saying. It says: אם
לא בא להם יין בתוך המזון אלא לאחר המזון אחד מברך לכולם.
im lo ba lahem yayin betoch hamazon ella le-achar hamazon echad mevarech
lekulam. They're separate scenarios. One is a case where they're having it
during the meal, everybody makes for him or herself. The other is
a case after the meal, they didn't have it during the meal,
they just had it after the meal. In that case, one person
makes for everyone. But if you made during the meal, you don't
have to make after; during can cover after, at least that's that
opinion. And we basically פוסקים paskin to the degree, I mean, assuming
bracketing also changes of societal norms and so on, the general assumption
is that they are different. Wine for drinking with the meal for
washing down as opposed to wine drunk for the sake of drinking.
But again here part of the problem is that you have to
bridge from during the meal to after the meal, so they might
have to be also of a similar type, of the same category.
Didn't we learn that the wine drunk before the meal פוטר poter
the wine drunk after the meal? Those are both a drinking experience.
Right, no, but we still make a ברכה bracha on the זימון
בורא פרי הגפן zimun Borei Pri Hagafen even though we made a
קידוש Kiddush before, right? Don't we? So that is fundamentally... fundamentally different
nature? Yeah, that's a good point.
And you think that there we would also have that in דעת
da'as because we know it's coming. But אחר מזון achar mazon remember
here means without ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. It means like the meal
is over, but you haven't done ברכת המזון birchas hamazon yet. So
after ברכת המזון birchas hamazon it certainly, you know, that really cuts
it off. All of these cases are without ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon.
So
yeah, there's no problem for us making a ברכה. bracha. Yeah, yeah.
Those who say ברכה על היין בתוך הסעודה, bracha al hayayin b'soch
hase'udah, the ones who hold that they do say a ברכה, bracha,
that it does פוטר, poter, and it doesn't or then they if
does individual דעת da'as matter in that case? Yeah, so that's what
I was saying, it seems there that they have to be that
even if your דעת da'as is to cover, or certainly say it
could break them, but the question is, is it sufficient to connect
them? It seems there that it also needs to be qualitatively similar
in order to be connected even if you have דעת. da'as. That's
what it seems. Let's move on to the next piece. ברכה על
הפת פוטרת את הפרפרת. Bircha al hapas poteres es haperperas. על הפרפרת
לא פוטרת את הפת. Al haperperas lo poteres es hapas. So the
bread covers the פרפרת perperas whether it's מזונות mezonos or whatever, but
obviously this little thingy, the מזונות mezonos or little breadcrumbs doesn't exempt
the bread. Now that's interesting because according to תוספות Tosafos it's breadcrumbs.
It's sort of similar to the drinking wine and the washing down
wine, that even though they're both המוציא, ha-motzi, somehow we're saying that
they're qualitatively different, and one is before the meal and one is
during, and they can't connect. בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim sorry,
בית שמאי אומרים אף לא מעשה קדירה, Beis Shammai omrim af lo
ma'aseh kedeirah,
even things that are like cooked in a pot, which basically is
like porridge and stew. So what does that mean? So הגמרא the
Gemara says איבעיא להו, iba'ya l'hu, there are two very good ways
of reading this statement of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. בית שמאי רישא
פליגי או דלמא סיפא פליגי? Beis Shammai reisha pligi o dilma seifa
pligi? Is he going on the first half or the second half?
פליגי. Pligi. דקאמר תנא קמא, De-ka'amar Tanna Kamma, because here's the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma said at the beginning, ברכה על הפת פוטרת את
הפרפרת, Bircha al hapas poteres es haperperas, that if you make a
ברכה bracha on the המוציא ha-motzi it covers these little snacks, you
know, מזונותes mezonos or breadcrumbs or whatever they are. וכל שכן מעשה
קדירה, V'chol shekein ma'aseh kedeirah, and of course the המוציא ha-motzi would
cover like a porridge, which is more a staple of the meal.
ואתא בית שמאי למימר, Ve-asa Beis Shammai l'meimar, and then בית שמאי
Beis Shammai comes and says, לא מיבעיא פרפרת דלא פטרה, lo mi-ba'ya
perperas d'lo patra, I don't first of all I don't think it
covers the little snacks, וליהו פת, u-lehu pas, אלא אפילו מעשה קדירה
נמי לא פטרה, ela afilu ma'aseh kedeirah nami lo patra, it doesn't
even cover like the porridge during the meal. So what does it?
Maybe it only covers things that are there like as a שומיר,
shomir, like ללפת את הפת, le-lafes es hapas, you know, things that
are there to come as a real going with the bread, but
not סתם stam things during the meal. That's one way of reading
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. They basically say it covers nothing except things
that are coming straight with the bread. That's one way of reading
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. או דלמא, O dilma, or maybe סיפא פליגי,
seifa pligi, that he's arguing on the end of the משנה. mishna.
דקתני ברכה על הפרפרת לא פוטרת את הפת, De-katani bircha al haperperas
lo poteres es hapas, that the ברכה bracha on the פרפרת perperas
does not exempt the bread. פת הוא דלא פטרה, Pas hu d'lo
patra, it doesn't exempt the bread, אבל מעשה קדירה פטרה, aval ma'aseh
kedeirah patra, it'd exempt other מזונות mezonos like מעשה קדירה, ma'aseh kedeirah,
some type of a porridge. ואתא בית שמאי למימר ואפילו מעשה קדירה
נמי לא פטרה. Ve-asa Beis Shammai l'meimar ve-afilu ma'aseh kedeirah nami lo
patra. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it doesn't even cover the מעשה
קדירה, ma'aseh kedeirah, the פרפרת perperas is always somewhat distinct from those
things even though they're both presumably מזונות. mezonos. ולמאי דתיקו, U-lemai de-teiku,
we don't know, but in the end it doesn't really matter להלכה
le-halacha because we don't פוסק pasken בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Okay. Now
let's
try to at least read the beginning of this. היו יושבין כל
אחד. Hayu yoshvin kol echad. Everybody was sitting. This becomes this important
idea of you need הסבה haseiba and then you're a group and
then one person can make a ברכה ראשונה bracha rishona for the
whole group. So הגמרא the Gemara says הסבו אין לא הסבו לא.
haseibu in lo haseibu lo. It's only when you actually did הסבה
haseiba that makes you a group. רמינהו, Reminehu, I'll ask you on
this. We have a תוספתא. Tosefta. עשרה שהיו הולכים בדרך, Asara she-hayu
holchim baderech, ten people were going on the way. אף על פי
שכולם אוכלים מככר אחד, Af al pi she-kulam ochlim mi-kikar echad, even
though they're all eating off of the same loaf of bread, כל
אחד ואחד מברך לעצמו, kol echad v'echad mevareich l'atzmo, you make your
own ברכה. bracha. Now here it counts because it says ten and
you are it sounds like we're also talking about maybe only talking
about ברכת המזון. birchas hamazon. There seems to be an assumption that
what determines קביעת סעודה kvi'as se'udah together for first ברכה bracha and
for the last ברכה bracha is the same. So if you're all
just eating the same loaf of bread it doesn't help. There's no
הסבה. haseiba. So you still have to make separate ברכות, brachos, ראשונה
ואחרונה. rishona v'achrona.
ישבו לאכול, Yashvu le'echol, they sat down to eat, אף על פי
שכל אחד ואחד אוכל מככרו, af al pi she-kol echad v'echad ochel
mi-kikaro, even if everybody has their own sandwich, their own piece of
bread, the fact that you sat down defined it as you're being
קובע kovei together. אחד מברך לכולם, Echad mevareich l'kulam, one can make
for everyone. And again, even if that's ברכה אחרונה, bracha achrona, which
תוספות Tosafos says it sounds like, presumably it's the same הלכה. halacha.
So anyway you see it's about sitting. קתני ישבו, Katani yashvu, you
see sitting, אף על פי דלא הסבו, af al pi d'lo haseibu,
without הסבה. haseiba. So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, כגון דאמרי, kegon de-amri, like they said, ניזיל וניכול לחמא
בדוך פלן. neizail v'neichol lachma biduch f'lan. They said, let's go eat
over there. So even though you didn't do הסבה, haseiba, the fact
that basically you didn't just happen to come together at the cafeteria
table, you planned to eat together, let's all get together and have
a meal over there, that defines it as קביעת סעודה kvi'as se'udah
even without הסבה. haseiba. That definitely you can have nowadays. The question
is, can you do this without פת? pas? תוספות Tosafos argues that
you still תוספות Tosfos argues that you still need פת pas as
the only thing that can define it that's not in the גמרא.
Gemara. But there is no such concept as having a קביעות kevius
without פת. pas. Now the רמב״ם Rambam also uses the language in
the context of פת, pas, but then in the beginning of הלכות
ברכות Hilchos Brachos when the רמב״ם Rambam gives his overview of the
הלכות, halachos, so he says as follows: מכלל דברי סופרים לברך על
כל מאכל שאדם אוכל אפילו אם לא שבע ומכלל דברי סופרים לברך
על כל הנאה. mikelal divrei soferim levarech al kol maachal she'adam ochel
afilu im lo sava umikelal divrei soferim levarech al kol hana'ah. Then
he says, ואם קבעו עליו לברך שלש ברכות. ve'im kave'u alav levarech
shalosh brachos. What does ואם קבעו עליו ve'im kave'u alav mean? Does
it mean only bread? The רמב״ם Rambam doesn't specify bread there. There
is a whole long discussion in the אחרונים. acharonim. Does the רמב״ם
Rambam mean specifically bread? Or does the רמב״ם Rambam mean anything you
eat as a קביעות? kevius? Now practically speaking, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch does not allow for this. In other words, our הלכה halacha
is as follows: If we're having fruit or cake, so even if
we are fifty people together, we don't do זימון. zimmun. It's only
with פת. pas. That's our פסק. psak. We do it only if
we're eating bread. However, it's good to know that there's such a
thing as a זימון zimmun on wine. You don't have to eat
bread. If three people sit down and drink wine together, they can
do a זימון zimmun on the wine. The גמרא Gemara says that
the three of them should sit down and drink wine, that would
constitute a זימון. zimmun. However, that too is not done anymore. We
don't do a זימון zimmun for wine. Why? Because it's not common
to sit and drink wine. Most people don't drink wine in a
way of קביעות. kevius. Maybe in France or other places they drink
wine as a standard thing, but in most places, we don't drink
wine together as a regular occurrence of קביעות. kevius. So therefore we
don't do a זימון zimmun on wine.